Guide to the Abraham Joshua Heschel Papers, 1880, 1919-1998 and undated RL.10086
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Writings, 1880, 1921-1990s and undated; 6; 245 Boxes
  - Writings by Others, circa 1930s-1991 and undated; 12
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר תכלת מרדכי, undated (Box 300, Folder 18)
      Transliteration: Sefer Tekhelet Mordekhai
      Translation: The End of Mordechay
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר בינת משה, undated (Box 300, Folder 19)
      Transliteration: Sefer ּBinat Mosheh
      Translation: The Wisdom of Moses
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר הרי בשמים, undated (Box 300, Folder 20)
      Transliteration: Sefer ּHare Beśamim
      Translation: The Mountains of Fragrance
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר זכרון כהונה, undated (Box 300, Folder 21)
      Transliteration: Sefer ּZikhron Kehunah
      Translation: The Memory of Priesthood
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר כליל תפארת, undated (Box 300, Folder 22)
      Transliteration: Sefer Kelil Tifʼeret
      Translation: Absolute Splendor
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר באר יצחק, undated (Box 300, Folder 23)
      Transliteration: Sefer Beʼer Yitsḥaḳ
      Translation: Isaak's Well
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר אמרי אלימלך, undated (Box 300, Folder 24)
      Transliteration: Sefer Imre Elimelekh
      Translation: The Words of Elimelech
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר נחמד ונעים, undated (Box 300, Folder 25)
      Transliteration: Sefer Neḥmad ṿe-Naʻim
      Translation: Sweet and Pleasant
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר בית אהרן, undated (Box 301, Folder 1)
      Transliteration: Sefer Bet Aharon
      Translation: The House of Aaron
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר קב חן, undated (Box 301, Folder 2)
      Transliteration: Sefer Ḳav ḥen
      Translation: Measurement of Grace
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר כתר תורה, undated (Box 301, Folder 3)
      Transliteration: Sefer Keter Torah
      Translation: Crown of the Torah
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר ברכת אברהם, undated (Box 301, Folder 4)
      Transliteration: Sefer Birkat Avraham
      Translation: The Blessings for Abraham
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר אורח לצדיק, undated (Box 301, Folder 5)
      Transliteration: Sefer Oraḥ la-Tsadiḳ
      Translation: Guest of the Righteous
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר אמרי משה, undated (Box 301, Folder 6)
      Transliteration: Sefer Imre Mosheh
      Translation: The Words of Moses
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר אמרי נואם, undated (Box 301, Folder 7)
      Transliteration: Sefer Imre Noʻam
      Translation: The Words of Pleasure
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר דרך פקודים, undated (Box 301, Folder 8)
      Transliteration: Sefer Derekh Peḳudim
      Translation: The Path of Commands
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר גנזי יוסף, undated (Box 301, Folder 9)
      Transliteration: Sefer Ginze Yosef
      Translation: The Treasures of Josef
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר נזר ישראל, undated (Box 301, Folder 10)
      Transliteration: Sefer Nezer Yiśraʼel
      Translation: The Wreath of Israel
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר מראה יחזקאל, undated (Box 301, Folder 11)
      Transliteration: Sefer Marʼeh Yeḥezkel
      Translation: The Mirror of Ezekiel
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר רגל ישרה, undated (Box 301, Folder 12)
      Transliteration: Sefer Regel Yesharah
      Translation: The Path of Integrity
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר תוספות חיים, undated (Box 301, Folder 13)
      Transliteration: Sefer Tosafot Ḥayim
      Translation: The Tosafot of Life
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר יסוד יצחק, undated (Box 301, Folder 14)
      Transliteration: Sefer Yesod Yitsḥaḳ
      Translation: The Foundation of Isaak
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר דברי יחזקאל, undated (Box 301, Folder 15)
      Transliteration: Sefer Divre Yeḥezḳʼel
      Translation: The Words of Ezekiel
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר חומת אריאל, undated (Box 301, Folder 16)
      Transliteration: Sefer Ḥomat Ariʼel
      Translation: The Wall of Ariel
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר שובע שמחות, undated (Box 301, Folder 17)
      Transliteration: Sefer Śovaʻ śemaḥot
      Translation: The Satiation of Happiness
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר הישר והטוב, undated (Box 301, Folder 18)
      Transliteration: Sefer ha-yashar ṿeha-ṭov
      Translation: The Righteous and the Good
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר פרקי הנאזר, undated (Box 301, Folder 19)
      Transliteration: Sefer Pirḳe ha-Neʼezar
      Translation: The Sayings of the Courageous
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר אגרא דפרקא, undated (Box 301, Folder 20)
      Transliteration: Igra de-Firḳa
      Translation: The Reward for [Study]
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר מנחם ציון, undated (Box 301, Folder 21)
      Transliteration: Sefer Menaḥem Tsiyon
      Translation: The Comfort of Zion
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר דברי שמואל, undated (Box 301, Folder 22)
      Transliteration: Sefer Divre Shemuʼel
      Translation: The Words of Samuel
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר חיים וחסד, undated (Box 301, Folder 23)
      Transliteration: Sefer Ḥayim ṿa-ḥesed
      Translation: Life and Kindness
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר נהר שלום, undated (Box 301, Folder 24)
      Transliteration: Sefer Nehar Shalom
      Translation: The River of Peace
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר תורת חיים, undated (Box 301, Folder 25)
      Transliteration: Sefer Torat Ḥayim
      Translation: The Torah of Life
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר נאות דשא, undated (Box 301, Folder 26)
      Transliteration: Sefer Neʼot deshe
      Translation: Pleasent Pastures
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר שפתי צדיקים, undated (Box 301, Folder 27)
      Transliteration: Sefer Śifte Tsadiḳim
      Translation: Dwellings of the Righteous
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר אור ישראל, undated (Box 301, Folder 28)
      Transliteration: Sefer Or Yiśraʼel
      Translation: Light of Israel
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר פרי קדש הלולים, undated (Box 302, Folder 1)
      Transliteration: Sefer Peri ḳodesh hilulim
      Translation: Holy First Fruit
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר בית ישראלֹ, undated (Box 302, Folder 2)
      Transliteration: Sefer Bet Yiśraʼel
      Translation: House of Israel
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר ברית כהונת עולם, undated (Box 302, Folder 3)
      Transliteration: Sefer Berit Kehunat ʻOlam
      Translation: The Covenant with the Priests of the World
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר חשב האפוד, undated (Box 302, Folder 4)
      Transliteration: Sefer Ḥeshev ha-Efod
      Translation: The Idea of Ephod
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר כתבי קודש, undated (Box 302, Folder 5)
      Transliteration: Sefer Kitve ḳodesh
      Translation: Holy Scripture
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר חסד לאברהם, undated (Box 302, Folder 6)
      Transliteration: Sefer Ḥesed le-Avraham
      Translation: Grace towards Abraham
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר ליקוטים יקרים, undated (Box 302, Folder 7)
      Transliteration: Sefer Liḳuṭim Yeḳarim
      Translation: Precious Compilations
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר משמרת איתמר, undated (Box 302, Folder 8)
      Transliteration: Sefer Mishmeret Itamar
      Translation: Guard of Ithamar
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר מאור עינים, undated (Box 302, Folder 9)
      Transliteration: Sefer Me'or 'Enayim
      Translation: Lighting of the eyes
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר סידורו של שבת, undated (Box 302, Folder 10)
      Transliteration: Sefer Siduro shel Shabat
      Translation: Sidur of Shabat
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר ראשי בשמים, undated (Box 302, Folder 11)
      Transliteration: Sefer Rashe Beśamim
      Translation: The Heads of Fragrance
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר מאמר מרדכי, undated (Box 302, Folder 12)
      Transliteration: Sefer Maʼamar Mordekhai
      Translation: The Sayings of Morderchai
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר לב שמח, undated (Box 302, Folder 13)
      Transliteration: Sefer Lev śameaḥ
      Translation: Happy Heart
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר זריזותא דאברהם, undated (Box 302, Folder 14)
      Transliteration: Sefer Zerizuta de-Avraham
      Translation: Agility of Abraham
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר תורת אמת, undated (Box 302, Folder 15)
      Transliteration: Sefer Torat Emet
      Translation: Torah of Truth
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר ליקוטי מוהר"ן, undated (Box 302, Folder 16)
      Transliteration: Sefer Liḳuṭe Moharan
      Translation: Selections of Moharan [Rabbi Nachman of Breslov]
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר ברכת דוד, undated (Box 302, Folder 17)
      Transliteration: Sefer Birkat Daṿid
      Translation: Blessings of David
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר דרכי האמונה, undated (Box 302, Folder 18)
      Transliteration: Sefer Darkhe Emunah
      Translation: Paths of Belief
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר עשה טוב, undated (Box 302, Folder 19)
      Transliteration: Sefer ʻaśeh ṭov
      Translation: Positive Commandments
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר עטרת צבי, undated (Box 302, Folder 20)
      Transliteration: Sefer ʻAṭeret Tsevi
      Translation: Crown of Zvi
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר דעת משה, undated (Box 302, Folder 21)
      Transliteration: Sefer Daʻat Mosheh
      Translation: Knowlegde of Moses
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר הנותן אמרי שפר, undated (Box 302, Folder 22)
      Transliteration: Sefer Ha-Noten Imre Shefer
      Translation: The Giver of Good Words
    - [Prombaum Research]: ספר קהילת יעקב, undated (Box 302, Folder 23)
      Transliteration: Sefer Ḳehilat Yaʻaḳov
      Translation: Congregation of Jacob
    - [Rabbi Gershon and other texts], undated; 1 of 3 (Box 303, Folder 1)
      Contains part of a typescript assembling different texts of Hasidic interest.
    - [Rabbi Gershon and other texts], undated; 2 of 3 (Box 303, Folder 2)
    - [Rabbi Gershon and other texts], undated; 3 of 3 (Box 303, Folder 3)
    - [Rabbi Gershon and other texts], undated; 1 of 3 (Box 303, Folder 4)
    - [Rabbi Gershon and other texts], undated; 2 of 3 (Box 303, Folder 5)
    - [Rabbi Gershon and other texts], undated; 3 of 3 (Box 303, Folder 6)
    - רבי גרשון בקיטובר, undated; 1 of 3 (Box 303, Folder 7)
      Transliteration: R[av] Gershon B'Kitover
      Translation: Rabbi Gershon of Kitov
    - רבי גרשון בקיטובר, undated; 2 of 3 (Box 304, Folder 1)
    - רבי גרשון בקיטובר, undated; 3 of 3 (Box 304, Folder 2)
    - באריכט, ארכיון, undated (Box 304, Folder 3)
      Transliteration: Barikhṭ, Arkhiyon
      Translation: Report, archive
      Contains a list related to Hanover manuscripts, the transcription of a Hebrew text, as well as photographic reproduction and negatives of Hebrew manuscripts.
    - Revision of Vol. II, undated; 1 of 2 (Box 304, Folder 4)
      Contains photocopies of Jewish works and of bibliographical citations.
    - Revision of Vol. II, undated; 2 of 2 (Box 304, Folder 5)
    - עבודת הקודש, undated (Box 304, Folder 6)
      Transliteration: ʻAvodat ha-ḳodesh
      Translation: Sacred Work
      Includes typescript from unknown author entitled "Inconsistencies of 'Dialectical Materialism'" and Talmudic references on work.
    - [Sayings of Rabbis], undated; 1 of 2 (Box 304, Folder 7)
      Contains a long typescript about the sayings of various Rabbis.
    - [Sayings of Rabbis], undated; 2 of 2 (Box 304, Folder 8)
    - [Sefer kitvei Kodesh], undated; 1 of 2 (Box 305, Folder 1)
      Contains the negative reproduction of the book Sefer Kitvei Kodesh.
    - [Sefer kitvei Kodesh], undated; 2 of 2 (Box 305, Folder 2)
    - Shabat, undated (Box 305, Folder 3)
      Typescript for Hebrew translation of Shabbat: Its Meaning for Modern Man.
    - [The Ontology of Authority], undated (Box 305, Folder 4)
      Photocopied typescript of a paper by F. Earle Fox.
    - [Torah], undated (Box 305, Folder 5)
      Primarily typescripts which appear to be a small collection of writings from different individuals about the study of the Torah.
    - Trinity, undated (Box 305, Folder 6)
      Includes the essays "Heidegger and Theology" by Hans Jonas, "The Logic of Biblical Anthropomorphism" by E. LaB. Cherbonnier from the Harvard Theological Review and "Chapter One: Toward a Biblical Philosophy" from an unknown work.
    - [Typescript], undated (Box 305, Folder 7)
      Language(s): All materials in Hebrew, Aramaic, and Yiddish.
      Contains two manuscripts: 1) handwritten (Hebrew and Aramaic) copied pages (contents unknown); 2) incomplete typescript (Yiddish) seemingly on Warsaw Ghetto, Jewish people, and Holocaust.
    - [Untitled Manuscript], undated (Box 305, Folder 8)
      Annotated typescripts of a text that includes what appears to be poetry, pages 1-99. Author unknown, but references some of Heschel's work.
    - [Miscellaneous Document], circa 1940s (Box 306, Folder 1)
      A one page document containing a Hebrew story, in handwriting that is not Heschel's.
    - [Untitled Manuscript], undated (Box 306, Folder 2)
      Annotated typescripts of a text that includes what appears to be poetry, pages 100-226. Author unknown, but references some of Heschel's work.
    - Vol, undated (Box 306, Folder 3)
      Assorted notes, some on/for various essays (with subjects like "Changing Halach", "God Frees Captives," What is Between Now and Messianic Times?"). Also includes an article by Judah Rosenthal.